Okay, we need to get to the bottom of who Elon Musk really is.
Okay, so when did it all start?
It's not when or where, but who.
It starts with the world's oldest supermodel.
Her name is May, like the month, but with an E at the end.
Thanks for spelling my name, Elon.
It says May Haldeman immigrated from Canada to South Africa in 1950.
Twenty years later, she married Errol Musk.
And a year after that, in 1971, Elon was born.
Yeah, he always was very curious
and when he started reading anything he read he memorized I mean he he
knew exactly what he'd read.
I thought I was insane
Why do you think you're insane
because it was clear
that other people do not Would their mind wasn't exploding with ideas They would
they wouldn't understand you.
I hope they wouldn't find out
because they might like put me away
or something You thought that for a second.
Yes, he hated going to school
because the other kids like to follow him home
and they would throw soda cans at his head.
Wasn't his parents' marriage tumultuous?
Yeah, Errol was allegedly abusive.
Allegedly.
Did you suffer that kind of abuse?
Yes.
You know there was a saying in South Africa,
when you get divorced you stop falling in the shower
because every time you have a scene with bruises you said you fell in the shower.
Elon never talks about his father.
Why is that?
Whenever the topic of Errol arrives, members of Elon's family clam up.
They are in agreement that he is not a pleasant man to be around.
Errol was not a happy childhood.
My father has serious issues.
So he sought refuge in computer games, which got him into coding.
He made a space themed video game called Blaster.
What did video games do for you?
They made me want to learn how to program computers.
Because then I thought, well I could make my own games.
You get to control something.
Yeah, you can construct a little universe.
When I was in high school we called them geeks.
And it was not a compliment.
What is a geek?
Somebody who is obsessed with learning something,
mastering a skill set
or a body of knowledge and would rather do that than develop social skills.
I think on Wikipedia it says
that I was inspired by my father in terms of technology.
This is actually not true.
I think it needs to be corrected.
He's somewhat of a Luddite actually in many respects, particularly computers.
He didn't want to buy a computer
and refused to use computers and said they would never amount to anything.
As far as role
models, Neil Armstrong was one of his heroes.
That's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.
Do you think from your knowledge of the moon having been there
that it is going to be possible in the foreseeable future to set up
scientific bases there on anything like a large scale?
Oh, I'm quite certain that we'll have such bases in our lifetime.
That, right there, that's what gave Elon his purpose.
When I was growing up,
I'd read lots of books,
and they were very often set in the United States.
It seemed like a lot of new technology was being developed in the United States,
so I thought,
okay, I really want to work on new technology,
so I want to get to Silicon Valley.
Back in 1995,
there weren't very many people on the internet
and certainly nobody was making any money at all.
Most people thought the internet was going to be a fad.
In the following years, he founded Zip2 and then PayPal.
So this is an ATM.
What we're going to do is transform the traditional banking industry.
I met him when I was 18, he was 19.
We were at college.
Science fiction novelist Justine Wilson.
My fear is
that we become spoiled brats, that we lose a sense of appreciation and perspective.
How many kids did they have?
Six.
I'm only counting five.
I had a son who died at 10 weeks.
It was called a cis-related incident.
And I went to Burning Man, I think six times after that happened.
And I had a ritual I would do.
And I would go to the temple of loss.
But I always found a place on one of the walls
and I would write, Nevada Alexander Musk.
He was a good baby.
And then they would set the temple on fire.
And that ritual was incredibly comforting to me.
Did Elon ever talk about it?
No.
He just threw himself into his work.
There need to be things
that make you look forward to waking up in the morning.
You wake up in the morning,
you look forward to the day, forward to the future.
A future where we are a space-faring civilization
and out there among the stars, I think that's very exciting.
We create a parallel world to escape the world
that rejects us, or the world that we find too painful to live in.
But some people are
so good at doing this
and master such an amazing skill set
that they take their world
and they infuse it into our world and they change it.
And these are the people we call visionaries.
2008, the rocket company is not going well.
You had three failures.
Great.
The car company is hemorrhaging money.
Yeah.
Each month that passes is literally, costs us tens of millions of dollars.
I mean, we need to appreciate that.
And the American economy has tanked in the worst recession since the Great Depression.
Right.
This is serious.
This is a major threat for our economy.
Move it!
Move it there!
What was that year like for you?
And I'm getting forced, by the way.
And then came the betrayal.
Who betrayed him?
SpaceX's lack of experience bothers some NASA legends,
like Apollo astronauts Neil Armstrong and Gene Cernan.
But having cut my teeth in rockets more than 50 years ago,
I am not confident.
Now is the time to overrule this administration's pledge to mediocrity.
You know, there are American heroes who don't like this idea.
Neil Armstrong, Gene Cernan, and I wonder what you think of that.
I was very sad to see that,
because those guys are,
yeah, you know, those guys are heroes of mine, so it's really tough.
They inspired you to do this, didn't they?
Yes.
And to see them casting stones in your
direction?
It's difficult.
Did you expect them to cheer you on?
So they're hoping they would.
What are you trying to prove to them?
I think he understood at that moment that he would never fit in.
I think people can choose to be not ordinary.
You know, they can choose to not necessarily conform to the conventions
that were taught to them by their parents.
So yes, I think it's possible for ordinary people to choose to be extraordinary.
But the edge can be a very interesting place to be.
I mean it can be lonely
and painful and sometimes dangerous and I don't mean to underplay any of that.
But it's also the place
where something is in the process of turning into something else.
Revolution enters at the edges.
Well, we've spent part,
if not most,
if not all of our lives trying to amputate those parts of ourselves
that did not fit.
You know, we've tried to be pleasing
and we've tried to do what's expected and we suck at it.
And we eventually reach a point
where we realize
that we are
so depressed or stuck
or numbed out
that the only way to save ourselves is to figure out how to be
ourselves on purpose
before we call these people visionaries this is bad
before they have
that kind of success we have other words for them
when we call them you know geek
or outsider socially awkward weird a little different odd one out
when critics say you can't do this your answer to them is we've done it.
That's what outsiders do.
They don't change the world from within by fitting in or conforming.
They change the world by creating a new one.
Elon Musk visited Amber Heard late at night while Johnny was away.
They were also caught on camera together in the elevator of the building getting
a little bit handsy.
It hurts my brain and my heart.
I don't know what I did.
Had anyone brought this to your attention?
No, I was just looking at it.